{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During a conflict in this region, the Grey Wolves deployed one thousand militia under the guidance of Isgandar Hamidov. Mediation by Medetkhan Sheremkulov [[meh-det- KAHN sheh-rem-KOO-lof]] successfully ended the first conflict named for this region with the Bishkek Protocol. This region's de facto capital, Stepanakert [[step-AH-nah-kehrt]], experienced ethnic cleansing of its Muslim minority, leading to intervention by the government in Baku. Armenia and Azerbaijan fought multiple wars over, for ten points, what region in the South Caucasus, provisionally controlled by the Republic of Artsakh?",
      "answer": "Nagorno-Karabakh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was killed in action after spearheading an attack on a blockhouse during which he rallied troops with the cry “Come on, my good soldiers, your General calls upon you.” With the help of David Wooster, this man besieged Fort St. John, which was then under the command of Guy Carleton. A poem notes how this man died on a battlefield “ting'd with blood that gush'd from Moncalm's veins” during a campaign in which his forces were joined with those of Benedict Arnold. For ten points, name this Continental Army general who led the 1775 invasion of Quebec.",
      "answer": [
        "Richard Montgomery",
        "\"Elegy on the death of Gen. Montgomery\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An inscription found at Sant' Agata dei Goti suggests that this man built a temple to Serapis on the Quirinal Hill. The dediticii [[ded-ee-tee-KEE-ee]] who surrendered in combat were an exception to this man’s edict greatly extending Roman citizenship. A set of palaestras were found in a building named for this man containing a frigidarium. Following the Praetorian Guard’s assassination of his brother, Geta, this man became the sole ruler of Rome before himself being killed in 219. For ten points, name this eldest son of Septimius Severus and namesake of a large complex of Roman baths.",
      "answer": [
        "Caracalla or Marcus Aurelius Antoninus \"Caracalla\"",
        "Baths of Caracalla",
        "or Terme di Caracalla"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "On March 17, 1992, the Israeli embassy in this country was bombed by the Islamic Jihad Organization. That bombing occurred two years prior to a bombing in this country's capital of a Jewish Community Center called AMIA. This country's president, Carlos Saul Menem, ordered the release of files relating to this country's role in protecting Nazi war criminals, including Adolf Eichmann. For ten points, name this South American country, where Jewish journalist Jacobo Timerman wrote about the Dirty War.",
      "answer": [
        "Argentina",
        "Argentine Republic",
        "Republica Argentina 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A conflict over the imperial succession in this period gave rise to the Hogen Rebellion. Retired emperors withdrew to monasteries but still held influence over government during this period's \"Cloistered Rule, and beginning in this period, noble women began wearing a particular twelve-layered robe. The Fujiwara clan dominated politics during this period, in which a work known as The Pillow Book was written. The Taira [[tah-EE-rah]] clan was defeated at the end of this period during the Genpei War. For ten points, name this period of cultural flourishing in classical Japan.",
      "answer": [
        "Heian Period",
        "Heian jidai"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1977, one of these places was created after Steve Rubell and Ian Schrager converted a theatre. In 1986, one of these places in West Germany, known as La Belle, was bombed, prompting Ronald Reagan to order Operation El Dorado Canyon against Libya. Studio 54 was a prominent example of these locations, another of which was the site of Omar Mateen’s mass shooting in Florida. For ten points, name these locations which include Pulse in Orlando.",
      "answer": [
        "Nightclubs",
        "Music Club",
        "Discotheque",
        "Disco Club",
        "Dance Club",
        "Gay Bars"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An attempt to establish quotas to raise 140,000 troops in this country was part of a policy called the Union of Arms. The county of Rousillon [[roo-see-YOHN]] was in the Northeastern March of this country in the late-15th century. Italian Ambrogio Spinola conquered Breda while leading the army of this country, whose forces were devastated by the French at Rocroi [[roh-KWAH]], ending the dominance of this country's Tercios. For ten points, name this Great Power of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, once ruled by Philip II.",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Spain",
        "Reino de España"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Though not by Karl Marx, this work claims that humanity “does not passively submit to the presence of nature” in its section “The Point of View of Historical Materialism.\" Three years prior to this work, its author eschewed an ethical framework in a book titled The Ethics of Ambiguity. Divisions between “the subject” and “the Other” are drawn in this work, which argues that “one is not born but becomes” a member of the title group. Written by the lover of Jean-Paul Sartre, for ten points, what is this feminist book by Simone de Beauvoir [[boh-VWAH]]?",
      "answer": [
        "The Second Sex",
        "Le Deuxième Sexe 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote the music for The Plow That Broke the Plains for the U.S. government's Resettlement Administration. This rival of Aaron Copland chronicled the life of Susan B. Anthony and the women's suffrage movement in his opera The Mother of Us All. This music critic for the New York Herald Tribune drew from the lives of Ignatius of Loyola and Teresa of Avila for an operatic collaboration with Gertrude Stein. For ten points, name this American composer who wrote Four Saints in Three Acts.",
      "answer": "Virgil Thomson"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this occurrence, the central figure’s bodyguards, known as the “skullcrushers,” assassinated this event's perpetrator. Rexford Tugwell claimed that this event resulted in “a beneficent peace [throughout] the land.” The defeat of Benjamin Pavy may have contributed to this event, which was carried out by a physician from Baton Rouge named Carl Weiss. This event brought about the end of the Share Our Wealth program, led by its central Louisiana politician. For ten points, name this event in which a populist governor nicknamed “The Kingfish” was killed.",
      "answer": "Assassination of Huey Pierce Long Jr."
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One soldier in this battle, William Hoffman, wrote a diary of his experiences which was chronicled through the eyes of a doctor in a work by Heinz Konsalik. Anthony Beevor won a Wolfson Prize for a book about this battle, which was the subject of a Heinrich Gerlach novel about a Breakout at [its central location]. A work about the Survivors of [this battle] includes a number of “Eyewitness Accounts from the Sixth Army.” For ten points, name this World War Two battle on the Eastern Front with more than 1.1 million Soviet casualties alone.",
        "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Jewish Soviet war correspondent wrote the novels Stalingrad and Life and Fate about his experiences on the Eastern Front?",
        "answer": "Vasily Grossman or Vasily Semyonovich Grossman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An object set in place by this act was preceded by an object depicting the “Fugio.\" This act created an institution whose officers included an engraver, and this act authorized the creation of a building whose cornerstone was laid by David Rittenhouse. Harsh penalties against “debasement” were listed in this act, which authorized half and quarter eagles and called for an inscription of “United States of America” on certain gold and silver objects. Creating the U.S. Mint, for ten points, what was this act that dealt with hard currency?",
        "answer": [
          "Coinage Act of 1792",
          "Mint Act before \"Mint\" is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Fugio Cent was also named for what Founding Father who designed the coin and placed the aphorism, \"Mind Your Business\" along the bottom?",
        "answer": [
          "Benjamin Franklin",
          "Franklin Cent",
          "Franklin penny"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man once said, “Man will never be free until the last king is strangled with the entrails of the last priest.” This man's financial troubles were relieved when he was hired as the personal librarian to Catherine the Great. A three-part piece describing the structure of this man’s best-known work took the form of a “Preliminary Discourse” authored by Jean d’Alembert [[dah-lem-BEHR]]. That Enlightenment-era work assembled by this man included a number of supplements and extra volumes. For ten points, name this founder of the Encyclopédie.",
        "answer": "Denis Diderot ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Catherine the Great paid Diderot a salary comprised of what currency translating to \"pound\" in French? It was replaced by the Franc in 1795.",
        "answer": "Livres 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After the 1977 elections in this country, the UTHR-J organization accused the United National Party of orchestrating pogroms against this nation's second largest ethnic group. A 1983 pogrom in this country, called Black July, helped spark the first phase of this country's Eelam War One. This country became a republic and received its current name under the premiership of Sirimavo Bandaranaike [[bahn-dar-ah-NYE-keh]] in 1972. For ten points, name this South Asian country where a 25-year civil war ended in 2009 after this country's predominantly Sinhalese government defeated the Tamil Tigers.",
        "answer": "Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Sri Lankan Civil War, the Tamil Tigers occupied this northern city for much of the 1990s. Prior to the Civil War, this city, which sits on a namesake peninsula, was the second largest in Sri Lanka.",
        "answer": [
          "Jaffna or Yāḻppāṇam",
          "or Yāpanaya"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At least 4,000 prisoners were once sacrificed by this empire at a yearly event known as its namesake “Annual Customs.” Francisco Félix de Sousa was a chacha of Ouidah who helped a leader of this empire ascend to power. A military unit consisting entirely of women was known as the namesake Amazons of this empire, once led by Ghezo. The Fon people made up this empire, which declined following the abolition of the slave trade. For ten points, name this African empire based in modern-day Benin.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Dahomey or Dahomey Empire",
          "Annual Customs of Dahomey",
          "Dahomey Amazons"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1748, the Kingdom of Dahomey was defeated by the Oyo Empire, a state ruled by what West African ethnic group that also occupy Nigeria and Togo?",
        "answer": "Yoruba People or Ìran Yorùbá"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In describing this conflict, Major Meredith compared the targeted group to Zulu warriors in that both demonstrated heavy resistance even after being shot. George Pearce was called the “Minister of [this conflict],\" during which Lewis Guns were employed against a group in the Campion district. The failure of attempts to herd the central group, whose migration led to widespread destruction of crops, contributed to this event. Targeting a species of flightless animals, for ten points, what was this “war” against an Australian bird?",
        "answer": [
          "Great Emu War",
          "Minister of the Emu War"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lewis Gun was largely replaced by the \"K\" machine gun manufactured by what British company that also produced Britain's chief machine gun during World War One?",
        "answer": [
          "Vickers-Armstrongs Limited",
          "Vickers Machine Gun",
          "or Vickers K Machine Gun 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In an article titled “The Russian Menace,” this person argued that the U.S. military posed a threat to Russian citizens. Ian McLellan Hunter received writing credit on behalf of this person for Roman Holiday. A statue installed at Grand Junction depicts this person writing in a bathtub. This scriptwriter of Spartacus was blacklisted after refusing to testify before the House Un-American Activities Committee. For ten points, what screenwriter was a part of the Hollywood Ten and inspired a film starring Bryan Cranston?",
        "answer": "Dalton Trumbo or James Dalton Trumbo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trumbo wrote the screenplay for Thirty Seconds Over Tokyo a film about what retaliatory 1942 airstrike by U.S. forces?",
        "answer": "Doolittle Raid"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Glenn Greenwald wrote an article criticizing this organization’s decision to forgo the word “torture” when describing tactics used by the Bush administration toward terrorism suspects. In 2017, tweets by this organization quoting the Declaration of Independence were labeled by critics as “propaganda” against Donald Trump. The first broadcast of this organization was coverage of the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations hearings on the Vietnam War on April 20, 1971. For ten points, what American news broadcaster operates as a non-profit media network?",
        "answer": "NPR or National Public Radio"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What flagship news program of NPR has been anchored by Ari Shapiro, Mary Louise Kelly, and Alisa Chang and had its first episode preserved by the Library of Congress?",
        "answer": "All Things Considered or ATC"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s nephew, Felix, led some of the revolts within the Ten Tragic Days alongside Bernardo Reyes. This man took power using the Plan of Tuxtepec, which disavowed the presidency of Sebastian Lerdo de Tejada. This man’s inner circle of advisors included Ramon Corral and Jose Yves Limantour and were known as the cientificos. This issuer of the Plan of San Luis Potosi was eventually ousted by Francisco Madero. For ten points, identify this longtime Mexican dictator who was overthrown in the Mexican Revolution.",
        "answer": "Porfirio Diaz or José de la Cruz Porfirio Díaz Mori"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Porfirio Diaz first rose to prominence after rising up against what Liberal politician, the first indigenous president of Mexico?",
        "answer": "Benito Juarez or Benito Pablo Juárez García 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 2002 case between this company and Step Two centered on internet personal jurisdiction. After returning from World War Two, Charles Lazarus founded this company after a stint selling cradles from his father’s bicycle shop. In 2017, this company filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy after having lost much of its market share to online retailers. Tru Kids owns the brand for this company, whose iconic “spokes-animal” mascot was Geoffrey the Giraffe. For ten points, name this retailer of children’s products that closed all of its U.S. locations in 2021.",
        "answer": "Toys “R” Us"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A developer of what Israeli air-defense system claimed that, due to budget constraints, certain missile components were built from repurposed cars bought from Toys \"R\" Us?",
        "answer": [
          "Iron Dome",
          "Kippat Barzel"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Tammany Hall",
      "prompt": "Concerning the New York political machine called Tammany Hall, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President and successor of Andrew Jackson whom it supported.",
          "answer": "Martin van Buren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Immigrant ethnic group which it assisted following the Potato Famine.",
          "answer": "Irish-American"
        },
        {
          "question": "First leader and former vice president who shot and killed Alexander Hamilton.",
          "answer": "Aaron Burr Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Boss depicted as a portly man with a money bag for a head in Harper's Weekly.",
          "answer": [
            "William Magear Tweed",
            "Boss Tweed"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Harper's Weekly cartoonist who depicted it as a tiger killing democracy.",
          "answer": "Thomas Nast"
        },
        {
          "question": "First major Catholic presidential candidate who lost the 1928 election to Hoover.",
          "answer": "Al Smith or Alfred Emanual Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native tribe, sometimes known as the Delaware, whose Chief Tamanend named Tammany Hall.",
          "answer": [
            "Lenape ] or Lënapeyok",
            "Leni Lenape"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest-serving boss who \"cleaned it up\" and supported John Francis Hylan for New York City mayor.",
          "answer": "Charles Francis Murphy 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "World War One Technology",
      "prompt": "Concerning military innovations during World War One, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Chemical weapon, with mustard and chlorine variants, used at the Battle of Ypres [[ee-PRUH]].",
          "answer": [
            "Poison Gas",
            "Chemical Weapons",
            "any answer with Gas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Vehicles known as \"landships,\" produced to break the stalemate of trench warfare.",
          "answer": "Tanks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Airships named for a German count which conducted bombing missions on Britain.",
          "answer": [
            "Zeppelins",
            "Ferdinand von Zeppelin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Bird whose \"Racing Homer\" breed was extensively used to relay messages.",
          "answer": "Pigeons"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conveyance used by the German Radfahr reconnaissance unit.",
          "answer": "Bicycles Editor's Note: \"Radfahr\" is German for \"Cycling\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Underwater detection system, early varieties of which were tested by the British \"Anti-Submarine Division.\"",
          "answer": "SONAR or Sound Navigation and Ranging"
        },
        {
          "question": "Striped camouflage used to make merchant ships harder to hunt.",
          "answer": [
            "Dazzle Camouflage",
            "Razzle Dazzle",
            "or Dazzle Painting"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British slang for the Stielhandgranate [[shteel-hahnd-grah-NAH-teh]] due to its similarity to a kitchen tool.",
          "answer": "\"Potato Masher\" 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mau Mau Uprising",
      "prompt": "Concerning the rebellious Mau Mau movement, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern East African nation where it occurred.",
          "answer": "Republic of Kenya or Jamhuri ya Kenya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ugandan dictator who fought the Mau Mau as a member of the King's African Rifles.",
          "answer": "Idi Amin or Idi Amin Dada Oumee"
        },
        {
          "question": "First president of the nation who supposedly masterminded the uprising.",
          "answer": [
            "Jomo Kenyatta",
            "Kamau wa Ngengi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Valley\" which is partially in Western Kenya and contains the African Great Lakes, the site of British detention centers like Marigat",
          "answer": "Rift Valley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader whose 1957 capture and hanging weakened the revolt.",
          "answer": [
            "Dedan Kimathi",
            "Dedan Kimathi Waciuri",
            "or Kimathi wa Waciuri"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Author who partially set his novel, A Grain of Wheat, during the uprising.",
          "answer": [
            "Ngugi Wa'Thiong'o ]",
            "James Ngugi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European-dominated region, seized by the Mau Mau, whose settlement first occurred under Sir Charles Eliot.",
          "answer": "White Highlands"
        },
        {
          "question": "1959 massacre of detained dissidents by British and African colonial guards.",
          "answer": [
            "Hola Massacre",
            "Hola Scandal 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this organization once allegedly said, “We are not at war with the administration…just do the work.” One CEO of this organization, who has chaired the Ronald Reagan Presidential Foundation, is Fred Ryan. (20 pts)",
        "During an interview with David Rubenstein, a leader of this organization spoke of the importance of scrutinizing public figures. After his work at The Boston Globe, Marty Baron became editor of this publication, which was purchased for $250 million by Jeff (10 pts)",
        "Bezos of Amazon. For ten points, name this daily newspaper serving the D.C. metropolitan area."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Washington Post",
        "\"WaPo\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) American physician Samuel Gridley Howe wrote a \"Historical Sketch\" named for this conflict while serving as a surgeon. Prior to this war, the fraternal brotherhood Filiki Eteria attempted to recruit future president, and Tsar Alexander's foreign minister, John Capodistrias (20 pts)",
        "to lead this revolt. Eugène Delacroix [[deh-lah- KWAH]] immortalized a tragedy during this war in his painting (10 pts)",
        "Massacre at Chios [[KYE-ohss]], and Lord Byron died from fever outside Lepanto during this war. For ten points, name this 1821 anti-Ottoman revolt which included the Battle of Navarino and the Siege of the Acropolis."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Greek Independence War or Greek War of Independence",
        "the Greek Revolution of 1821",
        "Elliniki Epanastasi",
        "Agonas but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Historian William of Newburgh stated that this work would be believed by someone \"ignorant of ancient history\" and wrote that the author \"lied about everything.\" This work was directly inspired by the Venerable Bede's Ecclesiastical History. (20 pts)",
        "This book ends with the Battle of Camlann, where both Mordred and his father fall in battle, resulting in the rise of the (10 pts)",
        "Anglo-Saxon kings. Geoffrey of Monmouth wrote a pseudohistorical account in, for ten points, what 12th century book that popularized the legend of Arthur?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Historia Regum Britanniae",
        "The History of the Kings of Britain",
        "De gestis Britonum",
        "On the Deeds of Britons"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this process, one man was presented with a silk screen landscape of the Huangshan Mountains, whereas the only thing that man had to offer in turn was a comb. This process was partly caused by Glenn Cowan missing his (20 pts)",
        "team's bus in Nagoya, after which he enjoyed a fifteen-minute conversation with three-time world champion Zhuang Zedong. Paving the way for (10 pts)",
        "Nixon's visit to a certain country, for ten points, what was this early 1970s series of events between players of a \"racquet\" sport that eased diplomatic tensions between the U.S. and China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ping-Pong Diplomacy Pīngpāng wàijiāo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The First Lateran Council, convened by Pope Callixtus II, reaffirmed an agreement in this city which included the emperor giving up his right to present ecclesiastics with a crosier. That \"Concordat\" in this European city, initially convened by (20 pts)",
        "Holy Roman Emperor Henry V, ended the 12th century Investiture Controversy. A 1521 assembly in this city, convened by Charles V, followed the papal bull Exsurge Domine, which aimed to refute some articles of the Ninety-five Theses. (10 pts)",
        "Martin Luther was declared a heretic during a diet [[DEE-et]] in, for ten points, which Rhenish city?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Worms ]",
        "Diet of Worms",
        "Concordat of Worms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jesus was once labelled the \"Crucified\" member of this philosophical tradition by Lucian in his work Peregrinus. While in a debate with Pericles, one member of this philosophical school asked, \"Who is to blame if an athlete is killed by javelin?\" (20 pts)",
        "wondering if one \"blames the javelin, the thrower, or the host of the games.\" A dialogue supposedly exposing this tradition's flaws, Gorgias, is named for an early figure in this movement known as \"The Nihilist.\" Protagoras [[proh-tah-GOH-rahs]] was (10 pts)",
        "an early figure in, for ten points, which Pre-Socratic school whom Plato depicted as charlatans?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sophists or Sophistic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Concerning his plans to create this opera, the composer once asked, “Who doesn’t know about the story of Zeus and Semele”? A silent role was given to Gottfried in this opera, which features the Ottonian king, Henry the Fowler. Based on a character appearing in a work by Wolfram von (20 pts)",
        "Eschenbach [[EH-shehn-bahk]], this work’s central character arrives aboard a boat headed by a swan to guard a noblewoman named Elsa. Many weddings (10 pts)",
        "feature the bridal chorus of this opera whose main character is the son of Parzival. For ten points, name this opera by Richard Wagner about a knight of the Holy Grail."
      ],
      "answer": "Lohengrin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As a youth, one man told this figure that he would be “a capable minister in peaceful times and an unscrupulous hero in chaotic times.\" In one portrayal, this man presented the Seven (20 pts)",
        "Gems Sword as a gift to another after a failed assassination attempt. This man lost what may have been the largest naval battle in history, after which he fled along the Dongting Lake. A lack of support among the populace of Jing province contributed to this man’s defeat at Red (10 pts)",
        "Cliffs against the army of Liu Bei. The state of Wei was led by, for ten points, what warlord of the Three Kingdoms era?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cao Cao ] generously",
        "differing pronunciations like ]",
        "Mengde 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician once quipped that he would never get ulcers, because he says exactly what he thinks. Benjamin Ward was appointed as police commissioner by this man whose tenure included the Howard Beach incident. Al Sharpton (20 pts)",
        "organized protest marches in response to the death of the sixteen-year-old Yusef Hawkins during this man’s mayoral administration. The 100th anniversary of the Brooklyn Bridge’s 1889 completion was celebrated under this predecessor of (10 pts)",
        "David Dinkins. For ten points, name this Jewish-American mayor of New York City from 1978 to 1989."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ed Koch",
        "Edward Irving Koch"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man legendarily was forced into exile to the Mema Kingdom with his sisters and mother due to a jealous wife of his polygamous father, Sassouma (20 pts)",
        "Bereté [[sah-SOO-mah beh-reh-TEH]]. This ruler's defeat of the sorcerer-king and Sosso leader Soumaoro Kanté was recounted by oral poets known as djeli [[JEH-lee]] in the Epic of this monarch. The founder of the (10 pts)",
        "Keita Dynasty was, for ten points, which mansa and leader of the Mandinke, the great-uncle of Mansa Musa?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sundiata Kieta",
        "Manding Diara",
        "or Sogolon Djata",
        "or Nare Maghan",
        "or Sogo Sogo Simbon Salaba"
      ]
    }
  ]
}